Guide to the Bernard Lafferty Papers, 1952-1999 (bulk 1993-1996)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bernard Lafferty papers 1952-1999 (bulk 1993-1996)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lafferty, Bernard, 1945-1996
7 linear feet Extent: 1,875 Items
Bernard Lafferty was hired as Doris Duke's butler in 1987 and he remained in that position until her death in 1993. In her will Doris Duke named Bernard Lafferty as the executor of her estate and for a brief period of time he was President of the Doris Duke Foundation. After a lengthy trial disputing the provisions of the will, Bernard Lafferty surrendered his post as co-executor and membership in the Foundation. He was replaced by a Board of Trustees who took control over Doris Duke's assets. Bernard Lafferty died in 1996, where upon he willed his assets to the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. The collection spans the years 1952-1999, although the majority of the collection is concentrated in the years 1993-1996. The holdings in this collection are from Bernard Lafferty's personal files and include condolences after the death of Doris Duke, memoranda and correspondence regarding daily business activities of Doris Duke's estates and of the Foundation, invitations, meeting notes, lists of visitors to Duke Farms, and requests for donations.
laffertybernard
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, however there are restrictions on certain materials within the collection. See Series level descriptions for more information.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Bernard Lafferty Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a donation from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in June 2009.
Biographical Note
Bernard Lafferty was hired as Doris Duke's butler in 1987 and he remained in that position until her death in 1993. In her will Doris Duke named Bernard Lafferty as the executor of her estate and for a brief period of time he was President of the Doris Duke Foundation. After a lengthy trial disputing the provisions of the will, Bernard Lafferty surrendered his post as co-executor and membership in the foundation. He was replaced by a Board of Trustees who took control over Doris Duke's assets. Bernard Lafferty died in 1996, where upon he willed his assets to the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation.
Collection Overview
The Bernard Lafferty Papers (formerly MSS.004) are part of the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation Historical Archives which were donated to the Duke University David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library by the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. The collection spans the years 1952-1999, although the majority of the collection is concentrated in the years 1993-1996. The holdings in this collection are from Bernard Lafferty's personal files and include condolences after the death of Doris Duke, memoranda and correspondence regarding daily business activities of Doris Duke's estates and of the Foundation, invitations, meeting notes, lists of visitors to Duke Farms, and requests for donations (both personal and through the Doris Duke Foundation). Also included are a variety of photographs, many of them with Doris Duke, and a few personal effects of Doris Duke including personal correspondence and address books.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Lafferty, Bernard, 1945-1996; Duke, Doris, 1912-1993; Doris Duke Foundation
Related Material
Doris Duke Papers, 1798-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Foundation Records, 1934-2009 (bulk 1948-1982)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Contents of Collection
- Administrative Records, 1952-1999 (bulk 1993-1996)
  RESTRICTED: Access to several folders in boxes 1 and 4 are restricted and require prior written approval from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation to view.
  - Ann Bachman to Bernard Lafferty, 17 Apr. 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from Peggy Lee to Bernard Lafferty, 1992 Feb 14, and thank you letter from Bernard Lafferty to Elizabeth Taylor, 1993 Nov 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Resumes and response memoranda for a position at the Doris Duke Foundation. Includes an Annual Report for the Geraldine R. Dodge Foundation, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Access restricted
  - General correspondence and messages taken for Bernard Lafferty, 1993 Oct-Nov (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence sent from Bernard Lafferty regarding Miss Duke's passing, Duke Farms manager's meetings, and meetings with financial consultants. Includes photographs of the Duke Homestead in Durham, NC 1993 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memoranda sent to Bernard Lafferty from Marianne Bowles regarding correspondence/memoranda which she sent on his behalf, 1993 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence sent from Bernard Lafferty thanking people for their condolences on Miss Duke's passing. Nov. 1993- Dec.1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Condolence cards sent to Bernard Lafferty and the Doris Duke Foundation after the passing of Doris Duke, 1993 Nov (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence from Carole Myers to Bernard Lafferty regarding Doris Duke's passing, 1993 Nov (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Telephone messages taken for Bernard Lafferty, 1993 Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence to and from Bernard Lafferty regarding condolences on Miss Duke's passing, 1993 Dec (1 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence to and from Bernard Lafferty regarding condolences on Miss Duke's passing, 1993 Dec (2 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence to and from Bernard Lafferty regarding condolences on Miss Duke's passing, 1993 Dec (3 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Irwin Bloom to B. Lafferty and to Doris Duke. Letters and other materials in original folder entitled "Bernard Confidential", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Congratulatory card for Bernard Lafferty from Victoria Principal and Dr. Harry Glassman, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence from Ron Protas, Martha Graham Center of Contemporary Dance, Inc. to Bernard Lafferty, and Bernard's reply correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence with Christie's and Sotheby's regarding the oil on canvas painting, "Christ and the Adulteress", 1993-1994, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Files maintained by Marianne Bowles, assistant to Bernard Lafferty, primarily concerning daily business activities. Includes some personnel issues, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence sent out which accompanied gifts sent by Bernard Lafferty, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence and memoranda sent to and from Bernard Lafferty, 1994 Jan-Jun (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and memoranda sent to and from Bernard Lafferty, 1994 Jan-Jun (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda sent to Bernard Lafferty, mostly from Marianne Bowles, regarding policies he put into effect at Duke Farms and his daily activities, 1994 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda sent to Bernard Lafferty, mostly regarding phone messages for him, courses taken by Bernard's secretary, Marianne Bowles, and policies put into effect by Bernard at Duke Farms, 1994 May-Aug (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence regarding N.J. Governor Christine Todd Whitman visiting Duke Farms, 1994 May 25 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and memoranda sent to and from Bernard Lafferty, primarily regarding his daily business activities, 1994 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Memoranda sent to Bernard Lafferty. Memos pertain to the Doris Duke Foundation donations, doctors appointments, and the various residences. Includes newspaper clippings, 1994 Sep-Nov (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence sent to Bernard Lafferty, mostly from friends and relatives of Miss Duke, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Memoranda sent to Bernard Lafferty. Memos pertain to the Doris Duke Foundation donations, personal phone messages, and U.S. Trust. Includes newspaper clippings. May 1995-Aug. 1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda sent to Bernard Lafferty. Primarily pertain to the Doris Duke Foundation donations, manager's reports, and appointments. Includes newspaper clippings, 1995 Jan-Apr (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda sent to Bernard Lafferty. Primarily pertain to the Doris Duke Foundation donations, manager's reports, and appointments. Includes newspaper clippings, 1995 Jan-Apr (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Phone messages for Bernard Lafferty, 1995 May-1996 May (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Memorandum to Bernard Lafferty from his secretary, Marianne Bowles, regarding insurance for his dogs, 1995 Aug (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Memoranda to Bernard Lafferty. Memos pertain to Doris Duke Foundation donations, pet care, and Bernard's personal requests. Includes newspaper clippings, 1995 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Memoranda sent from Bernard Lafferty, mostly regarding policies put into effect at Duke Farms. Includes numerous letters sent to the Duchess of York, Sarah Ferguson, 1995 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Memoranda and mail receipts for shipments of Bernard Lafferty's personal belongings to him in California. Includes photographs, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Memoranda sent to Bernard Lafferty from his secretary, Marianne Bowles, primarily concerning the Doris Duke Foundation, 1996 Jan-May (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Memoranda sent to Bernard Lafferty from his secretary, Marianne Bowles, primarily concerning the Doris Duke Foundation, 1996 Jan-May (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Christmas cards and postcards. Includes miscellaneous business cards, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Mail sent to Bernard Lafferty while he was at Falcon Lair. Contains mostly newspaper clippings regarding the estate of Doris Duke, 1996 Jan-May (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bernard Lafferty's Personnel File, 1987-1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Phone messages for Bernard Lafferty, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Address books, circa 1993-1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Passport applications and related forms and memoranda, 1993-1995 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Agreement written by Colin Kennedy for sale of Doris Duke's 737 airplane, 1994 Apr (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Mail receipts for shipments of mail to Bernard Lafferty while he was at Falcon Lair. Contains mostly memoranda regarding Duke Farms and newspaper clippings regarding the Estate of Doris Duke, 1995 May-Aug (1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Mail receipts for shipments of mail to Bernard Lafferty while he was at Falcon Lair. Contains mostly memoranda regarding Duke Farms and newspaper clippings regarding the Estate of Doris Duke, 1995 May-Aug (2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and other items stored in the Solarium safe. Includes letters to Doris Duke from Gloria Swanson and Imelda Marcos, typewritten note by Doris Duke, and Doris Duke's drivers licenses (2), 1952-1993 and undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence sent to Bernard Lafferty, mostly while he was at Duke Farms, 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Bernard Lafferty's datebook. Includes passage about how Miss Duke is to be laid to rest, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Bernard Lafferty's datebook/address book, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photo album of Bernard Lafferty's. Includes photographs of an unidentified wedding, photographs of Bernard Lafferty and Doris Duke, and photographs of laying Miss Duke to rest by putting her ashes in the ocean, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Doris Duke's address books (3), circa 1990s and undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Doris Duke's Honorary Deputy Sheriff's Badge, Palm Beach, FL, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Bernard Lafferty at locations such as Duke Farms, Shangri La, Rough Point, and Falcon Lair, 1989-1990s (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Doris Duke, Bernard Lafferty, and others in Vietnam, 1991-1992 (1 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Doris Duke, Bernard Lafferty, and others in Vietnam, 1991-1992 (2 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Honolulu, presumably staff laying wreaths in memory of Doris Duke, circa 1990s (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of boat trip and passengers on the trip to lay Miss Duke to rest at sea, 1994 Nov 22 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of laying of wreaths at Rough Point on first and second anniversary of Doris Duke's death, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Bernard Lafferty at different functions. Includes some original DDCF Trustees: J. Carter Brown, Marion "Oatsie" Charles, James Gill, and Nannerl O. Keohane, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Doris Duke, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Photograph of Bernard Lafferty and Elizabeth Taylor, circa 1980s-early 1990s (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, many of Bernard Lafferty. Includes photographs of Bernard Lafferty and Elton John. Also includes photographs of unknown house, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Bernard Lafferty alone and with Elizabeth Taylor and Sophia Loren, 1990-1992 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Bernard Lafferty and Elizabeth Taylor, 1994 Feb 3 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Photograph of Bernard Lafferty, Victoria Principal, Dr. Harry Glassman, and unidentified woman, circa mid-1990s (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Bernard Lafferty's home, Villa Palladio in Beverly Hills, CA, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 14)